# **Xincheng Huang**

Phone: 734-263-4841 | Email: xchuang@cs.ubc.ca | Website: https://xincheng.me

#### RESEARCH INTERESTS

My current research focuses on bridging the physical and virtual worlds in remote AR/VR collaboration. To do so, I create novel interactive techniques in Mixed Reality by combining state-of-the-art technologies from machine learning and sensing. From sharing a slice of physical surfaces to fully immersive environments, I hope my endeavor will make future telepresence and remote collaboration more seamless and natural. My research along this target has led to publications to IMWUT, TVCG, and UIST. Recently, I have been trying to incorporate emerging technologies such as neural rendering and generative AI into remote collaboration.

## **EDUCATION**

### University of British Columbia, Vancouver, BC

Sept 2021 – present

Ph.D. in Computer Science *Advisor: Dr. Robert Xiao* 

# University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI

Aug 2019 – April 2021

M.S. in Computer Science and Engineering

Advisors: Dr. Nikola Banovic and Dr. Alanson Sample

# New York University Shanghai, Shanghai, China

Aug 2015 – May 2019

B.S. with double major in Computer Science and Interactive Media Arts *Graduated with Magna Cum Laude* 

## RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Graduate Research Assistant. University of British Columbia, Vancouver, BC

Sept 2021 - present

X Lab. Advised by Dr. Robert Xiao

Enhancing the multi-modal interactivity of remote shared experience in AR/VR. So far, I have explored physical surface sharing and ad-hoc virtual replica creation for remote MR collaboration [J3], and 360° Video VR telepresence with 5G millimeter wave and multi-access edge computing [J2].

### Research Assistant. University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI

Mar 2020 – April 2021

Computational HCI Lab. Advised by Dr. Nikola Banovic and Dr. Alanson Sample

Conducted a research project as the first author on inferring assembly structures from user behaviors [J1]. This work utilized UHF-RFID sensing to profile the movement data of building blocks during assembly tasks, and then inferred the structures being built in real-time given the movement profile with Markov Chain Monte Carlo.

**Research Assistant.** University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI

Jan 2020 – April 2020, Jan 2021 – April 2021

Secure Cloud Manufacturing Group. Advised by Dr. Kira Barton

Created an educational Virtual Manufacture Space in VR for the Detroit Area Pre-college Engineering Program (DAPCEP). Presented two iterations of the project, based on VR and WebGL, on DAPCEP 2020 and DAPCEP 2021.

**Undergraduate Research Assistant.** New York University, New York City, NY

Jan 2018 – Dec 2018

New York University – Guggenheim. Conserving Computer-based Art Initiative. Advised by Prof Deena Engel Conducted code analysis for a software-based art: Color Panel, by John F. Simon Jr. 1998. Compiled the results of code analysis and suggestions for conservation in a 20-page report archived by the Guggenheim Museum.

### **PUBLICATIONS**

- [C1] Xincheng Huang\*, Michael Yin\*, Ziyi Xia, Robert Xiao. 2024. VirtualNexus: Enhancing 360-Degree Video AR/VR Collaboration with Environment Cutouts and Virtual Replicas. In *The 37th Annual ACM Symposium on User Interface Software and Technology (UIST '24), October 13–16, 2024, Pittsburgh, PA, USA*. ACM, New York, NY, USA, 12 pages. (To appear. Access preprint <a href="here">here</a>)
- [J3] Xincheng Huang and Robert Xiao. 2023. SurfShare: Lightweight Spatially Consistent Physical Surface and Virtual Replica Sharing with Head-mounted Mixed-Reality. *Proc. ACM Interact. Mob. Wearable Ubiquitous Technol.* 7, 4, Article 162 (December 2023), 24 pages. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/3631418">https://doi.org/10.1145/3631418</a>.
- [J2] Xincheng Huang, James Riddell, and Robert Xiao. 2023. "Virtual Reality Telepresence: 360-Degree Video Streaming with Edge-Compute Assisted Static Foveated Compression", in *IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics*, doi: 10.1109/TVCG.2023.3320255.
- [J1] Xincheng Huang, Keylonnie L. Miller, Alanson P. Sample, and Nikola Banovic. 2023. StructureSense: Inferring Constructive Assembly Structures from User Behaviors. *Proc. ACM Interact. Mob. Wearable Ubiquitous Technol.* 6, 4, Article 204 (December 2022), 25 pages. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/3570343">https://doi.org/10.1145/3570343</a>.
- [T2] Zhanghao Chen\*, Xincheng Huang\*. 2019. 3D Point Cloud Registration Algorithms for the Telewindow. Undergraduate thesis for Computer Science at New York University Shanghai. Advised by Dr. Olivier Marin and Prof. Michael Naimark.
- [T1] <u>Xincheng Huang</u>. 2019. Immersive Strategies: A First-Person Perspective Chess Game in VR. Undergraduate thesis for Interactive Media Arts at New York University Shanghai. Advised by Dr. Alison De Fren.

(\*: equal contribution)

#### TEACHING AND MENTORING

### **Graduate Teaching Assistant**

Sept 2022 – Dec 2022

University of British Columbia, Vancouver, BC

CPSC 554X – Machine Learning and Signal Processing. Duties: grading and responding to student questions.

# **Learning Assistant**

Feb 2019 – May 2019

New York University Shanghai, Shanghai, China

CSCI-SHU 101 Introduction to Computer Science. Duties: holding tutoring office hours, conducting review sessions, and facilitating class activities. Received award for "Excellent Tutoring" and "Most Appointed Office Hour".

### **Undergraduate Mentoring**

Dieter Frehlich, undergraduate student at *University of British Columbia*Junkai (Kelvin) Ding, undergraduate student at *University of British Columbia*James Riddell, undergraduate student at *University of British Columbia*, then M.S. at *University of Waterloo*Keylonnie Miller, undergraduate student at *University of Michigan*, then *Facebook* 

#### **ACADEMIC SERVICE**

## Reviewed 11 papers in various journals and conferences:

SUI 2024, VRST 2024, CHI Play 2024, IMWUT 2024, ISMAR 2024, CHI 2024, UIST 2023, CHI 2023

### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Assistant Software Engineer, PwC Service Deliver Center, Shanghai

July 2018 - Oct 2018

*SAP Department*. Developed SAP-based APIs for financial reports, material, and storage management using ABAP and OpenSQL.

#### **AWARDS**

MITACS Accelerate 2023-2024

Conducting Project *Rich, Immersive AR/VR communication* in collaboration with *Rogers Communications Canada Inc.* with a Mitacs Accelerate award with 60000 CAD.

### Latin Award, Magna Cum Laude, New York University Shanghai

2019

Awarded to top 15% of the graduated class

Dean's List for Academic Year, NYU Shanghai

2015 - 2016, 2016 - 2017, 2017 - 2018, 2018 - 2019

Awarded to top 30% for each academic year

University Recognition Award, NYU Shanghai

2017 - 2018

### **LEADERSHIP**

### ENACTUS NYU Shanghai, Vice President

2016 - 2017

Led the NYU Shanghai's branch of <u>ENACTUS</u>, a world-wide social entrepreneurial student organization. Participated in the user interviews, product design, and prototyping for our project: "A Third Eye: A Digital Blind Crutch". Won the *First prize* and the *Best technology innovation* award in ENACTUS social innovation competition of East China, and an 80000 CNY (~12000 USD) grant from the Chinese Charity Association (Shenzhen).